Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- D
  - Duggan, Donal, Jul 31, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Donal Duggan (b. Ballintotis, Co. Cork, Ireland, 1962) is a musician who emigrated in 1985 to relatives in Weston, Massachusetts, where he worked as a landscaper, received a Donnelly visa, married, and returned to Ireland in 1994.
  - Dunne, Martin, Jan 22, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Martin Dunne (b. Mullinahone, Co. Tipperary, 1939) emigrated to the United States in the 1950s and is a member of the Tipperary Association.
  - Dunne, Vincent, Nov 13, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Mr. Dunn discusses a range of topics, beginning with his childhood growing up in Sunnyside, Queens. After failing out of St. Teresa’s Catholic School, Woodside, Queens, in the 7th grade, Dunn went on to finish the year at St. Anthony’s Catholic School in Greenpoint, Brooklyn. At the age of 16 Dunn dropped out of Queens Vocational High School and began a series of part-time jobs that lasted for a year. When he was 17 Dunn enlisted in the Navy. He was stationed in Guantanamo, Cuba for four years, and was discharged at the age of 21.
    Dunn discusses his time in the Navy where he completed the G.E.D. (General Equivalency Diploma). While in the service, he also prepared for the city civil service test. He took the exam for the fire service. After passing the test and returning to New York, Dunn began his career as a fireman. He quickly climbed up the ranks of the fire service, moving from rookie fireman to deputy chief, lieutenant, and captain. Dunn then returned to school with the help of the G.I. Bill, and applied to Queens College in New York. Eventually, he received his Bachelors and Master’s Degrees. In 1959, at the age of 24, Dunn married his wife Patricia. He tells of the purchase of their first house in Douglaston, New York and the decoration of its backyard with stone faces and gargoyle statues acquired from torn down buildings in Harlem.
    Dunn retired in 1999 after serving 42 years as a fireman. Two years later the attacks on the World Trade Center occurred. Dunn remarks upon the construction of these buildings and their collapse. He shares that much of his life post-retirement is spent writing articles and giving lectures on the topic of building construction and fire-safety.
    Vincent Dunn was interviewed on 13 November 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Karen Shua-Haim and Linda Dowling Almeida. This oral history with Vincent Dunn was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 1 hour, 56 minutes long, on two CDs and had been logged at ten minute intervals.
    Vincent Dunne (b. Queens, New York, 1935), a forty-two year veteran of the New York Fire Department who writes and lectures nationally on fire and firefighter safety.
  - Dunphy, Michael P., May 4, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Michael P. Dunphy (b. Ballinakill, Co. Laois, 1944) emigrated to New York with his family at age 10. He is the past president of the Laois County Association of New York.
  - Dwyer, Jim, Nov 11, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Jim Dwyer (b. New York, New York, 1957) is the son of Irish immigrant parents from Co. Kerry. He is a Puliter Prize-winning writer for the New York Times and has published four books, including 102 Minutes: The Incredible Story of My Fight to Survive Inside the Twin Towers.
  - Dwyer, Phillip, Mar 9, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Phillip Dwyer (b. Sneem, Co. Kerry, Ireland, 1926, d. New York, NY, 2014) was drafted into the Army after emigrating to the United States in 1949. He became an electrician and settled on the Upper West side of Manhattan with his wife and children.
- E
  - Early, John F., Mar 1, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    John F. Early (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1943), a graduate of New York University, worked for the Irish Arts Center in the 1970s. He was a member of the Eagle Tavern group which split off from the Irish Arts Center in the mid 1980s.
  - Egan, Norah, Mar 29, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Norah Egan (b. Co. Westmeath, Ireland, 1974) grew up in Co. Longford and moved to the United States in the early 1990s. Since then she had worked as a childcare provider for several families in and around New York City.
  - English, Peter, Oct 16, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Peter English (b. Arklow, Co. Wicklow, Ireland, 1923): Peter's father left for New York in 1922 and he and his mother and siblings followed over and arrived in New York in 1928. The English family settled in the West Village/Chelsea area of New York, where there were a lot of Arklow people with strong connections to the Waterfront activities. Having served as a Marine, he joined the NYPD in 1950. He married a an Irish American, Mildred, who he had worked with. His son, Peter, followed his footsteps by joining the NYPD.
  - Enright, Thomas, Apr 25, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Thomas Enright (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1931) emigrated to the United States in 1956 and owns a garage in Queens. He became involved in Northern Irish activism and was part of several organizations including the American Congress for Irish Freedom and Irish Northern Aid Committee.
  - Evans, Tom, May 13, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Tom Evans (b. Bronx, New York, 1954), the son of immigrants from Skibbereen, Co. Cork and Ballingarry, Co. Limerick, grew up in Long Island City. His father was a long time member of New York's Cork Association and one of the few non-Catholic members in any county association at that time.
- F
  - Fallon, John J., Nov 16, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    John J. Fallon (b. Galway, Ireland, 1919, d. 2011) was the retired Principal of Bay Ridge High School and former president of the American Irish Teachers Association.
  - Fanning, Charles, Nov 4, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Mr. Fanning discusses his family background, his childhood in 1950s Norwood, Massachusetts, Irish American literature and his own academic and literary pursuits. Fanning begins the interview with background about his family. His father, Charles Fanning Sr., worked in a variety of jobs before settling as a custodian in Norwood public schools. The Fannings roots are in County Monaghan, Ireland. They immigrated during the famine and became farmers in Needham, Massachusetts. Fanning’s mother Frances Patricia Fanning never worked outside the home. Her mother was born in Cork because her parents, who had immigrated to Boston, had returned to Ireland to settle an estate.
    Fanning describes his childhood in Norwood which he remembers as an ideal time. He explains the separation in Norwood between the Irish, the Yankees and the new immigrants; mainly the groups were divided geographically by ethnic neighborhoods but there was no animosity between the communities. Fanning also talks about his family’s unique attitude towards the Yankees because in previous generations his family included intermarriages between Irish and Yankees.
    After attending public schools in Norwood, Fanning explains that he then attended Harvard University despite his guidance counselor’s urging to apply to Boston College. At Harvard, Fanning studied literature. When he graduated, he went to the University of California at Berkley where he pursued graduate studies in English. Fanning explains his interest shifted to teaching so he left Berkley to attend Harvard again for its graduate teaching programs. Fanning also admits while reviewing his education choices that fear of being drafted into the Viet Nam War kept him in school. In his final graduate program at the University of Pennsylvania in 1967, Fanning explains that he discovered his true passion while pursuing American studies and explored the connection between literature and history. Fanning wrote his dissertation on the work of Finley Peter Dunne which examined the Chicago Irish. Fanning also talks about his mentors John Kelleher, professor at Harvard, and Tom Brown at the University of Massachusetts, whose advice directed him toward Dunne.
    Fanning talks about his teaching career which began at Bridgewater State College in Massachusetts and the competition for teaching posts at the time he was finishing his PhD. He briefly mentions his two year stint teaching at the University of Missouri St. Louis before he went to Southern Illinois University at Carbondale where he founded an Irish studies program. Fanning talks about the reception of the Irish studies program which was positive in Carbondale. He also explains the extensive library of Irish literature at Carbondale which includes letters and manuscripts from Joyce and Yeats. Fanning also discusses Irish American literature at length and the future of Irish American literature.
    Fanning discusses his work beyond his dissertation, which he later developed into his first book published in 1968. He explains his writing process and his upcoming projects which include a memoir and a novel about Chicago in the 1880s.
    Charles Fanning was interviewed on 4 November 2009 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Tara Dougherty and Linda Dowling Almeida. The interview is 1 hour, 58 minutes, and 45 seconds long, on 2 CDs.
    Charles Fanning (b. Norwood, Massachusetts, 1942), Emeritus Professor of English at Southern Illinois University, Carbondale where he built a respected Irish Studies program, is the author of several works including The Irish Voice in America: Irish-American Fiction from the 1760s to the 1980s (1990) and Finley Peter Dunne and Mr. Dooley: The Chicago Years (2008). For 21 years, he taught at Bridgewater State College in Massachusetts and spent two years as assistant to the chancellor of the University of Missouri, St. Louis. A descendant of Famine immigrants from Co. Monaghan, his maternal grandmother was from Co. Cork.
  - Farragher, Michael and Eileen, Jun 20, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Michael and Eileen Farragher (b. Co. Galway, 1935) (b. Co. Limerick, 1941) met after emigrating from Ireland, married in 1965 and raised two sons in New Jersey. Michael, a US Army veteran, worked for the New Jersey Turnpike for 35 years. Their son is the writer Mike Farragher.
  - Farragher, Mike, Nov 1, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Mike Farragher (b. 1966) is the son of Irish-born parents from Cos. Limerick and Galway. He writes for the Irish Voice and Irishcentral.com and has published a series of essay collections entitled This Is Your Brain on Shamrocks.
  - Farrell, Brendan P., Oct 9, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Brendan P. Farrell (b. New York, New York, 1964), a successful businessman, he developed XPS, software used throughout the globe in financial services and was Ernst & Young's Businessperson of the year in 2011.
  - Feighery, John, May 1, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    John Feighery (b. 1933), a printer, is the son of 1920s immigrants from County Offaly and County Tipperary, Ireland. He is a member of the County Offaly Association as well as a volunteer coach and athletic director at his Bronx alma mater, Sacred Heart School, in Highbridge, NY.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on May 1, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Feighery, Nancy, Jun 23, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Nancy Feighery (b. Tullamore, Co. Offaly, 1934) studied nursing in Liverpool, England, before coming to America at the age of 20 in 1955. She married in 1960; she and her husband then moved back and forth between Ireland and New York with their children several times through the late 1960s and 1970s. They have owned and operated the Fiddler's Green, an Irish bar in Carmel, New York, since 1981.
  - Fine, Rosemary, Aug 21, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Rosemary Fine (b. Limerick City, Co. Limerick, Ireland, 1962) is an actor from an Irish Jewish family who toured the United States, married, re- located, and runs 'Java Joes' in Park Slope, Brooklyn.
  - Fitzgerald, Sr. Tesa, May 23, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Sr. Tesa Fitzgerald of the Sisters of St. Joseph (b. Far Rockaway, New York, 1946) is the daughter of immigrants from Counties Kerry and Donegal. She is the founder of Hour Children, a non-profit organization that provides support for incarcerated women and their families, in and out of the prison system.
  - Flanagan, Fionnula, Apr 15, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Fionnula Flanagan (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1941), a stage, television and film actress, has lived in Los Angeles since 1968. A fluent Irish speaker and a committed Irish nationalist, she is the wife of Dr. Garrett O'Connor.
  - Flanagan, James, Feb 17, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    James K. Flanagan (b. 1940), also known as Séamas Ó Flannagáin, is a poet and storyteller with roots in County Clare and County Roscommon, Ireland. A native of Jersey City, NJ, with a Ph.D. in English from the University of Notre Dame, he taught in Asbury Park and specialized in African-American literature.
    The interview focuses on themes like: being Irish in 1940s and 1950s Jersey city; Irish teenagers having romantic encounters with Italian teenagers; today’s blacks and latinos as the Irish of 150 years ago; Jersey City accent; parishes of Jersey City; Catholicism and politics in Jersey City; and the death of John Kennedy.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 300 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on February 17, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Flanagan, Rose; Mulvihill, Margie; Furlong, Patty, Feb 15, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rose Conway Flanagan, Patty Furlong, and Margie Mulvihill are all second generation Irish Americans raised in the Bronx, New York, are traditional Irish musicians. They play music together, as well as teach, in Rockland County and the New York City area.
  - Flannelly, Adrian (2 inteviews), Nov 13, 2008- Nov 19, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Adrian Flannelly (b. County Mayo, Ireland, 1942), a broadcast journalist, community leader and promoter, is a founding Board Member of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center, The Irish Repertory Theatre, and Ireland Chamber of Commerce USA (ICCUSA), as well as co-founder of Project Irish Outreach, Catholic Charities (Archdiocese of New York). He emigrated to New York in 1959 and has been broadcasting on local radio since the 1970s.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview took place over two sessions: November 13 and 19, 2008. The 11/13/08 interview is approximately 115 minutes long and the 11/19/08 interview is approximately 150 minutes long, on 5 CDs. The interview took place in New York City, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Fleming, Tom, Feb 27, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Some themes that are disscussed in the interview are: how does Irishness play out through his writing, and trying to escape his Irish American roots (track 17, 5 minutes); Irish versus Irish American; ‘all these god damn people remind me of my relatives!’re: Irish on his first trip to IRL in 1958 (track 19, 5 minutes); ‘I can’t do it. I can’t imagine how an American would think, that isn’t an Irish American. It was that strong.’ (track 17, 9 minutes); and Catholic versus Protestant in Jersey City (track 1).
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 3 hours and 15 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on February 27, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Tom Fleming (b. Jersey City, New Jersey, 1927), historian and novelist whose many published works have won main selections for the Book-of-the-Month Club in both fiction and nonfiction, is third generation Irish American. His 1961 novel All Good Men and his 2005 memoir Mysteries of My Father recall his childhood in Jersey City, New Jersey and the politics of the Frank Hague machine.
  - Flynn, Tom, May 11, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Tom Flynn (b. Albany, New York, 1946) is a descendant of Irish immigrants on both sides of his family tree, with known roots in Counties Waterford and Sligo. Dispersing from Canada and Boston, his ancestors ultimately found their way to New York State. Now a free-lance producer and author of a fledgling series of murder mysteries, he worked for 25 years at CBS News. He is the author of the epic poem, Bikeman, which recalls the morning of September 11, 2001.
  - Foley, Fr. John, Jul 13, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Fr. John Foley (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1940), Vice President of the Paulist Fathers, emigrated to New York at a young age. He was ordained as a Paulist priest in 1967 and served for over 44 years in New York, Texas, Rome, San Francisco and New Jersey. He earned a doctorate in canon law from Gregorian University in Rome and for 8 years was the Paulist liaison with the Vatican.
  - Forrester, Janet, Feb 12, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Janet Forrester (b. Kent, England, 1964) grew up in Northern Ireland and emigrated to the U.S. in the 1980s. A graduate of CUNY Law School with an MSW, she is a lawyer who represents parolees at Rikers Island, New York City's central prison.
  - French, Mary Carroll, Feb 2, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Mary Carroll French (b. 1963), a lawyer, is a second generation Irish American and life-long resident of Stuyvesant Town on Manhattan’s east side. Her mother is Martina Carroll and her brother is Patrick Carroll.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 100 minutes long. The interview took place in New York City on February 2, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
- G
  - Gardiner, Fr. Jim, Aug 8, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Fr. Jim Gardiner of the Dominican Order (b. Bronx, New York, 1942) is a Franciscan Friar and former director of Graymoor Spiritual Life Center in Garrison, New York. He worked with civil rights activists in Washington, DC, in the 1970s, and with AIDS patients in New York City in the 1980s and 1990s. He led the 22nd St. Patrick's Day Parade in Peekskill, New York, in 2011.
  - Geary, Karl, Mar 2, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    Karl Geary (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1972) is an actor and club owner who emigrated to the United States at the age of fifteen in 1987. He has appeared in several films and television shows, including Sex and the City, and wrote the film Coney Island Baby.
  - Gebhard, Catherine, Dec 3, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Catherine Gebhard (b. Limerick City, Co. Limerick, 1943), a nurse specializing in Oncology, Neurology and hospice care, emigrated to New York City with her parents in 1950. She raised 2 children on Long Island.
  - Gleeson, Sheila, Sep 18, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Sheila Gleeson (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1956) was lead immigration specialist at the Irish Immigration Center in Boston from 1995-2005, and later Director of the Coalition of Irish Immigration Centers, USA.
  - Glynn, Greg, Jun 5, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Greg Glynn (b. Oughterard, Co. Galway, Ireland, 1958) was co-founder of the Boston Irish Immigrant Reform Movement and a major advocate for immigration reform in the United States. He returned to Ireland in 1992 where he is partner in Arthur Cox and Company.
  - Goldman, Ira, Nov 11, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Ira Goldman (b. 1938), a government administrator, has been active in various Irish American organizations. Although his stock is primarily Jewish, he also identifies himself as Irish and believes that he holds an ancestral link to Famine immigrants from County Donegal.
    Some key themes discussed in the interview are: Jewish versus Irish identity; Northern Ireland; and race and religion.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview is approximately 200 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place on November 11, 2008, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Gormley, Sean, Oct 28, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Sean Gormley (b. Dublin, Co. Dublin, 1964) is an actor, film-maker and musician who wrote and directed the film Blackout (2006). A member of the Irish band, The Commitments, he emigrated to the U.S. with his American-born wife in 1997.
  - Gormley, Unateresa, Jun 15, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Unateresa Gormley (b. Bronx, New York, 1961), the daughter of immigrants from Counties Longford and Kerry, is a TCRG certified Irish dance teacher, and the founder and chairperson of the Big Apple Feis, as well as director of the Big Apple Rose of Tralee. She also serves as a volunteer for Project Children, hosting children from Northern Ireland for summers in the US.
  - Grall, Emer, Oct 24, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Grange, Fr. Sean (John), Oct 29, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Fr. Grange begins by discussing how his parents met on vacation at Rockaway Beach in Queens, New York. He talks extensively about his relatives and their experiences in New York. His grandparents on his mother’s side were both from Ireland, coming to the United States at an early age. His grandfather eventually became the manager of the Harvard Club of New York City, which along with his investments, allowed him to purchase a brownstone on Alexander Avenue, “the Irish Fifth Avenue,” in the South Bronx. Recalling his father’s side, Fr. Grange reveals that his grandmother had had three husbands prior to his grandfather. His grandfather and all of his uncles were policemen, and his aunt worked for the New York City Parks department. Fr. Grange compares his immigrant family’s entry into civil service positions with the current trend of Mexican immigrants joining the ranks of city employees.
    Although his mother’s parents did not talk much about Ireland, Fr. Grange explains that he does not think they were involved with the insurrections against the British around the time of the Easter Rising in 1916. Coming to the U.S. at very young ages, Fr. Grange believes they were told to leave home because there was not enough food, and as a result they never went back to Ireland. Instead, his grandfather participated in the Irish American community in New York, joining the annual Feis, an Irish dance and music competition. His father was a very steady man, refusing to drink because his younger brother died from alcoholism.
    Fr. Grange discusses his mother’s siblings, explaining how his mother’s eldest brother was thrown out of the New York Seminary. His aunt was a nun in the Sisters of Charity order. Another uncle was also temporarily thrown out of the seminary, but eventually organized a missionary group in Harlem in the 1930s, which conducted hundreds of conversions and baptisms a year for the predominantly African-American community that had migrated from the South in the 1920s. Discussing another aunt, Fr. Grange describes the abusive relationship she had with her husband. She is now the last survivor of that generation. The child born after her died early, which strongly affected Fr. Grange’s grandmother. Fr. Grange mentions that later in life, his grandmother had Alzheimer’s, which would cause her to sit in her rocking chair all day, waiting for her husband to return from work.
    Fr. Grange moves on to talk about his father’s side of the family in Rockaway Beach. He remembers going to their house and being bored because there were not many children to play with, and an episode in which they killed ducks in the backyard. Fr. Grange mostly interacted with his mother’s side of the family. His parents moved around to progressively larger apartments as his family grew, near his grandmother’s home on Alexander Avenue.